The Crucible Act 4 by Arthur Miller, Drama, Review and Inticipate
Is every defense in attack upon the court?
Hail asks in Act 3.
Danforth observes
A person is either with this court or he must be counted against it.
Such remarks stress the powerlessness of people like John Proctor and Giles Cori against
the mounting injustices in Salem.
In pursuing justice, their efforts backfire and their own names join the list of those
accused.
What do you think the final outcome will be?
Who will survive?
And who will perish?
Read the final act to see if your predictions are correct.
The Crucible Act 4 by Arthur Miller
Assel in Salem, jail, that fall.
With the back is a high-bard window, near it, a great heavy door, along the walls are two
benches.
The place is in darkness, but for the moonlight seeping through the bars, it appears empty,
presently, footsteps are heard coming down a corridor beyond the wall.
Keys rattle, and the door swings open.
Marshall Herrick enters with a lantern.
He is nearly drunk, and heavy-footed.
He goes to a bench and nudges a bundle of rags lying on it.
Zara, wake up, Sarah Good.
He then crosses to the other benches.
Sarah Good, rising in her rags.
Oh, majesty.
Common, common, Titchu-but, he's here.
His majesty's come.
Dirty north-cells, places wanted now.
He hangs his lantern on the wall.
Titchu-but sits up.
That don't look to me like his majesty.
Look to me like the Marshall.
Herrick, taking out a flask.
Get along with you now.
Clear this place.
He drinks, and Sarah Good comes, and pears up into his face.
Oh, is it you, Marshall?
I thought sure you'd be the devil common for us.
Could I have a sip of cider from a going away?
Herrick, handing her the flask.
And we off to Sarah, Titchu-but, and Sarah drinks.
We go into Barbados, soon the devil gets here with the feathers and the wings.
Oh, I happy voyage to you.
A pair of blueprints, winging suddenly the two of us.
Oh, it'd be a grand transformation, Marshall.
She raises the flask to drink again.
Herrick, taking the flask from her lips.
Get better give me that, or you'll never rise off the ground.
Come along now.
I'll speak to him for you if you desire to come along, Marshall.
Wait, Nat refuse it, Titchu-but?
It's the proper morning to fly into hell.
Oh, it'd be no hell in Barbados.
Devil, him be pleasure-man in Barbados, him be singing and dancing in Barbados.
It's you, folks.
You riles him up around here.
It'd be too cold around here for that old boy.
He frees his soul in Massachusetts, but in Barbados he just as sweet and…
A bellowing cow is heard, and Titchu-but leaps up and calls to the window.
I, sir.
That's him, Sarah.
I'm here, Majesty.
They heardly pick up the rags as Hopkins, a guard enters.
That that'd be the governor's arrived.
Herrick, grabbing Titchu-but.
Come along.
Titchu-but resisting him.
No, he coming for me.
I go at home.
Herrick, pulling her to the door.
That's not Satan, just a poor old cow with a head full of milk.
Come along now.
Out with you.
Titchu-but calling to the window.
Take me home, Devil.
Take me home.
Sarah good, following the shouting Titchu-but out.
Tell him I'm going, Titchu-but.
Now you tell him Sarah good is going to.
In the corridor outside, Titchu-but calls on.
Take me home, Devil.
Devil take me home.
And Hopkins' voice orders her to move on.
Herrick returns and begins to push old rags and straw into a corner.
Hearing footsteps, he turns, and enter, Danforth, and judge, Hathorn.
They are in great coats and where hats against the bitter cold.
They are followed in by chiever, who carries a dispatch case and a flat wooden box containing his
writing materials.
Good morning, Excellency.
Where is Mr. Paris?
Elfitu.
He starts for the door.
Marshall?
Herrick stops.
When did Revere hail arrive?
Withward midnight, I think.
Danforth, suspiciously.
What is he about here?
He goes among them that will hang sur and he prays with them.
He sits with goodie nurse now and is to Paris with them.
Indeed.
That ban have no authority to enter here, Marshall.
Why he will let him in.
What?
Mr. Paris command, Mr. I can not deny him.
Are you drunk, Marshall?
No, sir.
It is a bitter night and I have no fire here.
Danforth, containing his anger.
Fetch, Mr. Paris.
There is a prestigious stench in this place.
I have only not cleared the people out for you.
Beware, hard, drink, Marshall.
Nice, sir.
He waits in instant for further orders, but Danforth, in dissatisfaction, turns his back on
him.
And Herrick goes out.
There is a pause.
Danforth stands in thought.
Let you question hail, Excellency.
I should not be surprised he have been preaching in and over lately.
He will come to that speak nothing of Andover.
Paris praises with him.
That strange.
He blows on his hands.
Moves toward the window.
It looks out.
Excellency, I wonder if it be wise to let Mr. Paris so continuously with the prisoners.
Danforth turns to him.
Interested.
I think sometimes the man has a man look these days.
Mad?
I met him yesterday coming out of his house and I beat him good morning and he wept and went
his way.
I think it is not well the village sees him so unsteady.
Perhaps he have some sorrow.
Cheever, stepping his feet against the cold.
I think it be the cause, sir.
Cows?
There be so many cows wandering the high roads.
Now their masters are in the jails and much disagreement who they will belong to now.
I know Mr. Paris be arguing with farmers all yesterday.
There is great contention, sir, about the cows.
Contention making weeps, sir.
There is always a man that weep for contention.
He turns as to have thorn and Danforth hearing someone coming up the corridor.
Danforth raises his head as Paris enters.
He is gone, frightened and sweating in his great coat.
Paris to Danforth instantly.
Oh good morning, sir.
Thank you for coming.
I beg your pardon waking you so early.
Good morning, Judge Hathorn.
Have you ever in hell have no right to enter this?
Excellency am moment.
He hurries back and shuts the door.
Do you leave him alone with the prisoners?
What is business here?
Paris, prayerfully holding up his hands.
Excellency hear me.
It is a Providence Reverend Hale has returned to bring Rebecca nurse to God.
Danforth, surprised.
He bits her confess.
Paris, sitting.
Hear me.
Rebecca have not given me a word this three month since she came.
Now she sits with him and her sister and Martha Cory and two or three others and he pleads
with them.
Confess their crimes and save their lives.
Why?
This is indeed a Providence.
And they soften, they soften?
Not yet, not yet.
But I thought to summon you, sir, that we might think on whether it be not wise to.
He dares not say it.
I had thought to put a question, sir, and I hope you will not.
Mr. Paris, be plain but troubles you.
There is news, sir, that the court must reckon with.
Mind, niece, sir, mind.
I believe she has vanished.
Vanished?
I had thought to advise you about earlier in the week, but.
Why?
How long has she gone?
This be the third night.
You see, sir, she told me she would stay in night with Mercy Lewis.
And next day, when she does not return, I send to Mr. Lewis to inquire.
Mercy told him she would sleep in my house for a night.
They are both gone?
Paris in fear of him.
They are, sir.
Danforth, alarmed.
I will send a party for them.
Where may they be?
Excellency, I think they be aboard a ship.
And forth, stands a game.
My daughter tells me how she heard them speaking of ships last week.
And tonight I discover my, my strong boxes broken to.
He presses his fingers against his eyes to keep back tears.
Half-orn, astonished.
She helped robbed you.
31 pound is gone.
I am penniless.
He covers his face and sobs.
Mr. Paris, you are a brainless man.
He walks and thought deeply worried.
Excellency, it profit nothing you should blame me.
I cannot think they would run off except they fear to keep in seal them anymore.
He is pleading.
Markets, sir.
Abigail had close knowledge of the town and since the news of Andover has broken here.
Andover is remedied.
The court returns there on Friday and will resume examinations.
I am sure of it, sir.
But the rumor here speaks rebellion in Andover.
And it, there is no rebellion in Andover.
I tell you what is said, sir.
Andover have thrown out the court, they say, and will have no part of witchcraft.
There be a faction here feeding on that news and I tell you, tru, sir.
I fear there will be right here.
Right?
Why at every execution I have seen not but high set of spaction in the town.
Just, half-orn, it were another sort that hang till now.
Rebecca Nurse is no bridge that lived three years with Bishop before she married him.
John Proctor is not Isaac Ward that drank his family to ruin.
To Danforth.
I would, to God, it would not so, excellency.
But these people have great weight yet in the town.
Let Rebecca stand upon the gibbet and send up some righteous prayer and I fear shall
wake avenge on you.
Excellent, see.
She is condemned a witch.
The court have...
Danforth, indeed concerned, raising a hand to half-orn.
Pray, or to Paris.
How do you propose, then?
Excellency.
I would postpone these hangings for a time.
There will be no postponement.
Now, Mr. Hales returned.
There is hope, I think, for if he bring even one of these to God that confession surely
dams the others in the public eye.
And none may doubt more that they are all linked to hell.
This way, unconfessed and claiming innocence, doubts are multiplied.
Many honest people will wait for them and our good purpose is lost in their tears.
Danforth, after thinking a moment, then going to cheever.
Give me the list.
Cheever opens the dispatch case.
Searches.
It cannot be for God's sir that when I summon the congregation for John Proctor's excommunication,
there were hardly thirty people come to hear it that speak a discontent, I think, and
Danforth studying the list, there will be no postponement.
Excellency.
Now, sir.
Which of these, in your opinion, may be brought to God.
I will, myself, strive with him till dawn.
He hands the list to Paris, who merely glances at him.
"There is not sufficient time till dawn.
I shall do my utmost.
Which of them do you have hope for?
Paris.
Not even glancing at the list now.
And in a quavering voice quietly.
Excellency.
A dagger.
He chokes up.
What do you say?
Tonight, when I open my door to leave my house, a dagger clatter to the ground.
Silence.
Danforth absorbs this.
Now Paris cries out.
You cannot hang this sword.
There is danger for me.
I did not step outside at night.
Reverend Hale enters.
They look at him for an instant in silence.
He is steeped in sorrow, exhausted.
And more direct than he ever was.
Except my congratulations, Reverend Hale.
We are gladden to see you return to your good work.
Hale, coming to Danforth now.
You must pardon them.
They will not butch.
Haryc enters.
Wades.
Danforth, conciliatory.
You must understand, sir.
I cannot pardon these when twelve are already hanged for the same crime.
It is not just Paris, with failing heart.
Rebecca will not confess.
The sun will rise in a few minutes.
Excellency, I must have more time.
Now Hale and begari yourselves no more.
I will not receive a single plea for pardon or postponement.
Then that will not confess will hang.
Twelve are already executed.
The names of these seven are given out, and the village expects to see them die this morning.
Postpoment, I'll speak a floundering on my part.
Reprieve or pardon must cast out upon the guilt of them that died till now.
While I speak God's law, I will not crack its voice with whimpering.
If retaliation is your fear, know this.
I should hang ten thousand that dared to rise against the law, and an ocean of salt tears could not melt the resolution of the statutes.
Now, joyous cells up like men, and help me.
As you are bound by heaven to do, have you spoken with them all Mr. Hale?
All but proctor, he is in the dungeon.
Danforth, to heric.
What's proctor's way now?
He sits like some great bird, who'd not know he lived except he will take food from time to time.
Danforth, after thinking a moment.
His wife, his wife must be well on with child now.
Gee, sir, what thank you Mr. Paris, you have closer knowledge of this man, might her presence soften him?
It is possible, sir. He have not laid eyes on her these three months.
I should summon her.
Danforth, to heric.
Is he yet adamant?
Has he struck at you again?
He cannot, sir. He is jamed of the wall now.
Danforth, after thinking on it.
Fetch, could he proctor to me?
Then that you bring him up?
I sir.
Heric goes, there is silence.
Excellency, if you postpone a week and publish to the town that you are striving for their confessions,
that speak mercy on your part, not faltering.
Mr. Hale, is God have not empowered me like Joshua to stop this son from rising, so I cannot withhold from them the perfection of their punishment.
Hale, pardon me.
If you think God wills you to raise rebellion, Mr. Danforth, you are mistaken.
Danforth, instantly.
You have heard rebellion spoken in the town?
Excellency, there are orphans wandering from house to house, abandoned cattle, bellow on the high roads, the stink of rotting crops, hangs everywhere, and no man knows when the harlot's cry will end his life.
And you want to yet, if rebellion spoke, better you should marvel how they do not burn your province.
Mr. Hale, have you preached an end over this month?
Think God they have no need of me and an over.
You bath will me, sir. Why have you returned here?
Why? It is all simple.
I come to do the devil's work. I come to counsel Christians. They should belive themselves.
His sarcasm collapses.
There is blood on my head. Can you not see the blood on my head?
Hush, for he has heard footsteps. They all face the door.
Hale enters with a lizabeth. Her wrists are linked by heavy chain, which heric now removes. Her clothes are dirty. Her face is pale and gone. Herocos out.
Danforth, very politely.
Goodie, proctor, she is silent.
I hope you are hearty. Elizabeth, as a warning reminder.
I am yet six months before my time.
Frank, be at your ease. We come not for your life. We uncertain how to plead for he is not accustomed to it.
Mr. Hale, you speak with the woman?
Goodie proctor. Your husband is marked to hang this morning. Pause.
Elizabeth, quietly.
I have heard it.
You know, do you not have no connection with the court? She seems to doubt it.
I come of my own goodie proctor. I would save your husband's life for if he is taken, I count myself his murderer. Do you understand me?
What do you want of me?
Goodie proctor. I have gone this three month like I lored into the wilderness. I have sought a Christian way for damn nations doubled on a minister who counsels been to lie.
It is no lie, you cannot speak of lies.
It is a lie. They are innocent.
I'll hear no more of that.
Hale, continuing to Elizabeth.
Let you not mistake your duty as I mistook my own.
I came into this village like a bridegroom to his beloved bearing gifts of high religion.
The very crowns of holy law I brought and what I touched with my bright confidence.
It died. And where I turned the eye of my great faith, blood flowed up.
Beware, goodie proctor, cleave to no faith when faith brings blood.
It is mistaken law that leads you to sacrifice.
Life, woman, life is God's most precious gift.
No principle, however glorious, may justify the taking of it.
I beg you, woman, prevail upon your husband to confess.
Let him give his lie.
Quail not before God's judgment in this.
Fort may well be God, dams a liar less than he that throws his life away for pride.
Will you plead with him?
I cannot think you will listen to another.
Elizabeth, quietly.
I think that be the devil's argument.
Hale, with a climactic desperation.
Woman, before the laws of God we are a swine, we cannot read his will.
I cannot dispute with you, sir. I lack learning for it.
Danforth, going to her.
Goodie proctor, you are not summoned here for disputation.
Be there no wife the tenderness within you?
He will die with the sunrise, your husband, do you understand it?
She only looks at him.
What say you? Where you contend with him?
She is silent. Are you stoned?
I tell you true woman, had I know other proof of your unnatural life, your dry eyes now would be sufficient evidence that you delivered up your soul to hell.
A very ape would weep at such calamity.
Have the devil dried up any tear of pity in you?
She is silent.
Take her out. It profit nothing she should speak to him.
Elizabeth, quietly.
Let me speak with him, excellency.
Paris, with hope. You'll strive with him?
She hesitates.
Will you plead for his confession or will you not?
I promise nothing. Let me speak with him.
A sound, the civilins of dragging feet on stone. They turn.
A pause.
Heric enters with John Proctor.
His wrists are chained. He is another man.
Bearded. Filthy. His eyes misty.
As the webs head overgrown them. He halts inside the doorway.
His eyes caught by the sight of Elizabeth.
The emotion flowing between them prevents anyone from speaking for an instant.
Now hail.
Visibly affected. Goes to Danforth and speaks quietly.
Pray. Leave the mexuncy.
Danforth. Pressing hail impatiently aside.
Mr. Proctor. You have been notified. Have you not?
Proctor is silent. Staring at Elizabeth.
I see light in the sky, Mr.
Let you come so with your wife and may God help you turn your back on hail.
Proctor is silent. Staring at Elizabeth.
Hail. Quietly. Excellency. Let.
Danforth brushes past hail and walks out.
Hail follows. Chiever stands and follows.
Hathorn behind. Heric goes. Paris. From a safe distance offers.
If you desire a cup of cider, Mr. Proctor, I'm sure I.
Proctor turns an icy stare at him and he breaks off.
Paris raises his palms toward Proctor.
God lead you now. Paris goes out.
Alone, Proctor walks to her. Halt's.
It is as though they stood in a spinning world.
It is beyond sorrow. Above it. He reaches out his hand as though toward an embodiment.
Not quite real. An icy touches her. A strange soft sound. Half laughter.
Half amazement. Comes from his throat. He pats her hand.
She covers his hand with hers. And then weak. He sits. Then she sits. Facing him.
The child. It grows. There's no word of the boys.
They're well. Rebecca's Samuel keeps them.
You have not seen them? I have not. She catches a weakening in herself and downs it.
You are a marvellous Elizabeth. You have been tortured?
I. Pause. She will not let herself be drowned in the sea that threatens her.
They come for my life now. I know it. Pause. None. Have you had confessed?
There are many confessed. Who are they?
There are hundreds or more. They say. Goody ballad is one. I say a good kind is one.
There are many. Rebecca? Not Rebecca. She is one foot in heaven now.
Not may hurt her more. And child?
You have not heard of it? I hear nothing where I'm kept.
Child is dead. He looks at her incredulously. When where he hanged, Elizabeth quietly, factually.
He will not hanged. He would not answer I or nay to his indictment.
For if he denied the charge they'd hang him surely and auction out his property.
So he stand mute and died Christian under the law. And so his sons will have his farm.
It is the law for he could not be condemned a wizard without he answer the indictment. I or nay.
Then how does he die? Elizabeth, gently. They press him, John.
Press?
Great stones they lay upon his chest until he plead I or nay.
With a tender smile for the old man. They say he give them but two words.
More wait he says and died.
Proctor, numbed, a thread to weave into his agony.
More wait.
I, it wore a fearsome man, Giles Cory.
Pause.
Proctor with great force of will but not quite looking at her.
I have been thinking I would confess to them Elizabeth. She shows nothing.
What say you? If I give them that?
I cannot judge you, John.
Pause.
Proctor, simply a peer question. What would you have me do?
As you will I would have it.
Slight pause.
I want you living, John. That's sure.
Proctor, pauses. Then with a flailing of hope.
Child's wife, has she confessed?
She will not.
Pause.
It is a pretence Elizabeth.
What is?
I cannot mount the chip at like a saint. It is a fraud.
I am not that man. She is silent.
My honesty is broke Elizabeth.
I am no good man.
Nothing spoiled by giving them this lie that were not rotten long before.
And yet you have not confessed till now that speak goodness in you.
Spide only keeps me silent.
This is hard to give a lie to dogs.
Pause.
For the first time he turns directly to her.
I would have your forgiveness Elizabeth.
It is not for me to give, John. I am.
I'd have you see some honesty in it. Let them that never lie,
die now to keep their souls. It is pretence for me.
A vanity that will not blind God nor keep my children out of the wind.
Pause.
What's a you?
Elizabeth, upon a heaving sigh that always threatens.
John, it come to not that I should forgive you. If you will not forgive yourself.
Now he turns away a little in great agony.
It is not my soul, John. It is yours.
He stands as though in physical pain slowly rising to his feet with a great immortal longing
to find his answer. It is difficult to say as she is on the verge of tears.
Only be sure of this for I know it now.
Whatever you will do, it is a good man does it.
He turns his doubting, searching gaze upon her.
I have read my heart this three month, John.
Pause.
I have sins of my own to count. It needs a cold wife to prompt literary.
Proctor and great pain.
Enough and enough.
Elizabeth, now pouring out her heart.
Better you should know me.
I will not hear it. I know you.
You take my sins upon you, John.
Proctor and agony.
No. I take my own, my own.
John.
I counted myself so plain, so poorly made, no honest love could come to me.
Suspicion kissed you when I did.
I never knew how I should say my love. It were a cold house I kept.
In fright, she swears as half-orn enters.
What say a proctor? The sun is suit-up.
Proctor is chest-heaving, stairs.
Turns to Elizabeth. She comes to him as though to plead, or voice-quaking.
Do what you will, but let none be your judge.
There be no higher judge under heaven than Proctor is.
Forgive me for give me, John. I never knew such goodness in the world.
She covers her face, weeping.
Proctor turns from her to Hathorn. He is off the earth.
His voice, hollow.
I want my life.
Hathorn electrified, surprised.
You'll confess yourself?
I will have my life.
Hathorn, with a mystical tone.
God be praised. It is a providence. He rushes out the door,
and his voice is heard calling down the corridor.
He will confess. Proctor will confess.
Proctor with a cry as he strives to the door.
Why do you cry it?
And great pain, he turns back to her.
It is evil, is it not?
It is evil.
Elizabeth, in terror, weeping.
I cannot judge you, John. I cannot.
Then who will judge me?
Suddenly clasping his hands.
God in heaven.
What is John Proctor?
He moves as an animal, and the fury is writing in him.
Attentaly is to search. I think it is honest, I think so.
I am no saint.
As though she had denied this, he calls angerly at her.
Let Rebecca go like a saint.
For me, it is fraud.
Voices are heard in the hall, speaking together in surprised excitement.
I am not your judge. I cannot be.
As though giving him release.
Do as you will. Do as you will.
Would you give them such a lie?
Say it.
Would you ever give them this?
She cannot answer.
You would not.
It tongs of fire, or singing you, you would not.
It is evil.
Good then. It is evil, and I do it.
How Thorn enters with Danforth, and with them,
Cheever, Paris, and Hail.
It is a business like rapid entrance, as though the ice had been broken.
Danforth, with great relief and gratitude.
Praise to God, man.
Praise to God.
You shall be blessed and heaven for this.
Cheever has hurried to the bench with pen, ink, and paper.
Proctor watches him.
Now then, let us have it. Are you ready, Mr. Cheever?
Proctor with a cold, cold, horror at their efficiency.
Why must it be written?
My for the good instruction of the village, Mr.
This we shall post upon the church door.
To Paris urgently.
Where's the marshal?
Paris runs to the door and calls down the corridor.
Marshall, hurry.
Now then, Mr. We'll you speak slowly and directly to the point for Mr. Cheever's sake.
He is unrecognized and is really dictating to Cheever, who writes.
Mr. Proctor, have you seen the devil in your life?
Proctor's jaws lock.
Come, man. There is light in the sky that Hound waits at the scaffold.
I would give out this news.
Did you see the devil?
I did.
Praise God.
And when he come to you, what were his demand?
Proctor is silent.
Danforth helps.
Did he bid you to do his work upon the earth?
He did.
And you bound yourself to his service?
Danforth turns as Rebecca nurse enters with her helping to support her.
She is barely able to walk.
Come in, come in, woman.
Rebecca, brightening as she sees Proctor.
Ah, John. You are well, then, eh?
Proctor turns as face to the wall.
Courage, man. Courage.
That her witness your good example that she may come to God herself.
Now, here at Goode University.
Say, "On the projector, did you bind yourself to the devil's service?"
Rebecca astonished.
Why, John?
Proctor, through his teeth, his face turned from Rebecca.
I did.
Now, woman, you surely see it, profit nothing to keep this conspiracy, any further.
Will you confess yourself with him?
Oh, John.
God sent his mercy on you.
I say, will you confess yourself, Goode nurse?
Why?
It is a lie.
How may I damn myself?
I cannot.
Mr. Proctor, with the devil came to you, did you see Rebecca nurse in his company?
Proctor is silent.
Come, man, take courage.
Did you ever see her with the devil?
Proctor, almost inaudibly.
No.
Danforth, now sensing trouble, glances at John and goes to the table.
It picks up a sheet.
The list of condemned.
Did you ever see her sister, Mary Easty with the devil?
No, I did not.
Danforth, his eyes narrow and proctor.
Did you ever see Martha Corrie with the devil?
I did not.
Danforth, realizing slowly putting a sheet down.
Did you ever see anyone with the devil?
I did not.
Proctor, you must take me.
I am not empowered to trade your life for a lie.
You have most certainly seen some person with the devil?
Proctor is silent.
Mr. Proctor, a score of people have already testified.
They saw this woman with the devil.
Then it is proved.
Why must I say it?
Why must you say it?
Why you should rejoice to say it if your soul is truly perished of any love for help?
They think to go like saints.
I like not to spoil their names.
Danforth, inquiring.
Proctor, do you think they go like saints?
Proctor, evading.
This woman never thought she'd done the devil's work.
Look, you sir.
I think you must take your duty here.
It matter nothing what she thought.
She is convicted of the unnatural murder of children and you for sending your spirit out upon Mary Warren.
Your soul alone is the issue here, Mr.
And you will prove it's whiteness, or you cannot live in a Christian country.
Will you tell me now what persons conspired with you in the devil's company?
Proctor is silent.
To your knowledge was Rebecca Nurse, ever.
I speak by own sins.
I cannot judge another.
Crying out with hatred.
I have no tongue for it.
Hail quickly to Danforth.
Excellency, it is enough.
He confess himself.
Let him sign it.
Paras, feverishly.
It is a great service sir.
It is a waiting name.
It will strike the village that Proctor confess.
I beg you.
Let him sign it.
The sun is up.
Excellency.
Danforth.
Consitters.
Then with dissatisfaction.
Come, then.
Sign your testimony.
To cheever.
Give it to him.
Cheever goes to Proctor.
The confession and a pen in hand.
Proctor does not look at it.
Come, man.
Sign it.
Proctor after glancing at the confession.
You have all witnessed it.
It is enough.
You will not sign it.
You have all witnessed it.
What more is needed.
Do you spot with me?
You will sign your name.
Or it is no confession, Mr.
He has pressed heeding with agonized breathing.
Proctor now lays the paper down and signs his name.
Praise be to the Lord.
Proctor has just finished signing when Danforth reaches for the paper.
But Proctor snatches it up.
And now a wild terror is rising in him and a boundless anger.
Danforth, perplexed, but politely extending his hand.
If you please, sir.
No.
Danforth, as though Proctor did not understand,
Mr. Proctor, I must have...
No.
No, I have signed it.
You have seen me.
It is done.
You have no need for this.
Proctor, the village must have proof that...
Damn the village.
I confess to God and God has seen my name on this.
It is enough.
No, sir.
It is.
You came to save my soul.
Did you not hear?
I have confessed myself.
It is enough.
You have not confessed myself.
Is there no good penitence, but it be public?
God does not lead my name nailed upon the church.
God sees my name.
God knows how black my sins are.
It is enough.
Mr. Proctor, you will not use me.
I am no serer, good or ticuba.
I am John Proctor.
You will not use me.
It is no part of salvation that you should use me.
I do not wish to.
I have three children.
How am I teach them to walk like men in the world?
And I sold my friends?
You have not sold your friends.
Be guide me not.
I blacken all of them when this is nailed to the church the very day they hang for silence.
Mr. Proctor, I must have good and legal proof that you are the high court.
Your word is good enough.
Tell them I confessed myself.
Say Proctor broke his knees and we have like a woman.
Say what you will.
But my name cannot.
Danforth with suspicion.
It is the same is it not?
If I report it or you sign to it?
Proctor, he knows it is not saying.
No, it is not the same.
What others say and what I sign to is not the same.
Why?
Do you mean to deny this confession when you are free?
I mean to deny nothing.
Then explain to me Mr. Proctor while you will not let.
Proctor with a cry of his whole soul.
Because it is my name.
Because I cannot have another in my life because I lie and sign myself to lies.
Because I am not worth the dust on the feet of them that hang.
How may I live without my name?
I have given you my soul.
Leave me my name.
Danforth pointing at the confession in Proctor's hand.
Is that document a lie?
If it is a lie, I will not accept it.
What say you?
I will not deal in lies, Mr.
Proctor is motionless.
You will give me your honest confession in my hand or I cannot keep you from the rope.
Proctor does not reply.
What way do you go, Mr.
Proctor?
He has breast heaving his eyes staring.
Proctor tears the paper and crumbles it.
And he is weeping in fury but erect.
Marshall, Paris hysterically as though the tearing paper were his life.
Proctor?
Man, you will hang.
You cannot.
Proctor is eyes full of tears.
I can.
And there's your first marvel that I can.
You have made your magic now, for now I do think I see some shred of goodness in John Proctor.
Not enough to weave a banner with but white enough to keep it from such dogs.
Elizabeth, in a burst of tear, rushes to him and weeps against his hand.
Give them note here.
Tears pleasure them.
Show honor now, show a stony heart and sink them with it.
He has lifted her and kisses her now with great passion.
Let you fear nothing.
Another judgment waits us all.
Hang them high over the town.
Who weeps for these weeps for corruption.
He sweeps out past them.
Heric starts to lead Rebecca, who almost collapses.
But Proctor catches her and she glances up at him, apologetically.
I've had no breakfast.
Go, man.
Heric escorts them out.
Atheran and she ver behind them.
Elizabeth stands staring at the empty doorway.
Paris, intently fear, do Elizabeth.
Go to him, go to him, go to him, go to him, go to him, go to him, go to him.
There is yet time.
From outside a drumroll strikes the air.
Paris is startled.
Elizabeth jerks about toward the window.
Go to him.
He rushes out the door as though to hold back his fate.
Proctor, Proctor!
Again, a short burst of trumps.
Woman pleads with him.
He starts to rush out the door and then goes back to her.
Woman, it is pride.
It is vanity.
She avoids his eyes and moves to the window.
He drops to his knees.
Be his helper.
What profit him to bleed?
Shall the dust praise him?
Shall the worms declare his truth?
Go to him, take his shame away.
Elizabeth, supporting herself against collapse, grips the bars of the window, and with a cry.
He have his goodness now.
God forbid I take it from him.
The final drumroll crashes, then heightens violently.
Hail weeps in front of prayer, and the new sun is pouring in upon her face.
And the drums rattle like bones in the morning air.
The curtain falls.